Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, so today's דף daf is נ"ה. Nun
Hey. We pick up at the bottom of נ"ד עמוד ב' Nun
Daled Amud Bet and we had been discussing repeating things multiple times
with משה Moshe and אהרן Aaron four times, but then we had
the statement which was in contrast of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
said no, you have to teach it to your students so well
that he actually knows it and is able to say it over,
so it's maybe not even limited by four times. And now the
גמרא Gemara picks up and says the following:
כמאן אזלא, Keman Azla, it is one, two, three, six lines down
in the wide lines, end of the line, last four words. כמאן
אזלא הא דתניא, Keman Azla Ha Detanya, who's it going like that
which we taught in the בריתא? Baraita? I'm sorry, a little bit
earlier than that in the line, beginning of that line. אמר מר
רבי יהודה אומר לעולם אהרן לימין משה חוזר. Amar Mar Rabbi Yehuda
Omer Le'olam Aaron Limin Moshe Chozer. So after אהרן Aaron was sitting
at משה'ס Moshe's left, once there was somebody else to sit at
משה'ס Moshe's left, according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אהרן Aaron got
up and moved to משה'ס Moshe's right. So כמאן אזלא הא דתניא,
Keman Azla Ha Detanya, who's it going like that which we taught
in the בריתא? Baraita? שלשה שהיו מהלכים בדרך, Sheloshah Shehayu Mahalchim Baderech,
three people that were going on the way, הרב HaRav if there's
a rabbi among them, like one of them is the rabbi of
the other two, באמצע Ba'emtza is in the middle, וגדול בימינו Vegadol
Biyemino the larger, more important of the student on his right, וקטן
משמאלו Vekatan Mismolo and the less important on his left. So you
see the idea that the more important should always be on the
right. לימא רבי יהודה ולא רבנן? Leima Rabbi Yehuda Velo Rabbanan? Maybe
it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and not the rabbis? Because rabbis said
that אהרן Aaron was on משה'ס Moshe's left and stayed on משה'ס
Moshe's left. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבנן, Afilu
Teima Rabbanan, even rabbis agree that in principle the more important one
should be on the right. But משום טירחא דאהרן, Mishum Tircha De-Aaron,
but since what's implicit here is when you only have two you
don't want to sort of take be sort of presumptuous and go
to your רבי'ס Rebbe's right. So when there's only you and the
רבי Rebbe you start on the left. I'm going to tell you
when somebody else comes then you sort of arrange yourselves. So the
rabbis say once אהרן Aaron started on משה'ס Moshe's left, they didn't,
it was not going to sort of inconvenience him and have him
to get up and move over to the right. So it's a
question of
what does it matter whether your fork is on the right or
on the left or what order? Yeah because societies look at those
details as signs of that's the way society works is these types
of rules are used
as signifiers of various things. So I mean it's if you treat
it like, I guess your question is why is it becoming a
הלכה Halacha rather than just like a certain societal norm? Right. Right.
Shouldn't the one with the most knowledge being in the middle so
that those on the side could hear him because it's more...
It's not practical. It's not practical. It's like when you come to
a door you show honor to the more important one, you let
them walk in first, the תורה Torah like מפני שיבה תקום, Lifnei
Seiva Takum, there's certain types of things you do to show respect.
So different societies have different ways of symbolizing it and there's a
society in which the right is considered to be the more important
side, לב חכם לימינו ולב כסיל לשמאלו, Lev Chacham Liyimino Velev Ksil
Lismolo, so a way of showing respect is by arranging yourselves accordingly.
It's not
practical, it's a question
of what to call
almost etiquette issues. So etiquette are somewhat arbitrary rules but once the
rules are in place they signify things.
And then people have to decide which one of us is the
most...
I understand.
It can lead to that. I suppose that if there's no obvious
difference you wouldn't worry about it, I would hope so. All right
let's, right.
Right hand man. Right,
exactly.
Okay so let's continue. All right. So it says,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב פרידא הוי ליה
ההוא תלמידה, Rav Preida Havei Lei Hahu Talmida, רב פרידא Rav Preida
had a student דהוי תני ליה ארבע מאה זימני, Dehavei Tanei Lei
Arba Mea Zimnei, he had to teach him things 400 times. Imagine
it's a little bit of an exaggeration but anyway, meaning four wasn't
enough, it's like continuing the idea of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, 400
times. וגמר Vegamar and he finally learned it. יומא חד בעו ליה
מילתא דמצוה, Yoma Chad Ba'u Lei Milta Demitzva, one day they said
they told somebody came in and said רב פרידא Rav Preida was
needed for
some מצוה Mitzvah thing, we need you to make a מנין, Minyan,
we need you whatever, I don't know משמח חתן וכלה Mesameach Choson
Vekalla whatever it was. So he said fine fine let me finish
teaching my student. So תני ליה, Tanei Lei, so he taught him
the 400 times. ולא גמר Velo Gemar and he this time he
wasn't able to learn it after 400 times. אמר ליה, Amar Lei,
so רב פרידא Rav Preida said to him מה עידנא מאי שנא
Mah Idna Maishana why is today different you're not able to learn?
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, he said to him, מכדי האי שעתא דאמרו
ליה למר Midei Hai Shaita De'amru Lei Lemar from the moment they
said to the master you, איכא מילתא דמצוה Ika Milta Demitzva that
you had to get going because it was a מצוה Mitzvah thing,
אסחא לי דעתי Ascha Lei Da'ati I got distracted and I thought
וכל שעתא אמינא Vechol Shaita Amina everything every minute I was saying
השתא קאי מר השתא קאי מר, Hashta Kai Mar Hashta Kai Mar,
oh he's about to leave he's about to leave, so I wasn't
able to focus because I was always anxious you were about to
get up and go. So אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he said
to him, הב דעתך Hav Da'atach look, forget about that, I'm here
for you, pay attention ואתני לך Ve'asni Lach
and I will teach it to you. הדר תני ליה ארבע מאה
זימני אחריני, Hadar Tanei Lei Arba Mea Zimnei Achrinei, so he taught
him 400 times again. And then finally he got it. נפקא בת
קול ואמרה ליה, Nafka Bat Kol Ve'amra Lei, so a heavenly voice
came out and said ניחא לך, Nicha Lach, it is it is
appropriate for you deserving of you דליספו לך ארבע מאה שני, Deleispu
Lach Arba Mea Shani, you either have merited by this amazing... act
of dedication to your student to do anything to make sure that
he would learn it, you either merit you can get four hundred
extra years, או דתיזכו את ודורך לעלמא דאתי o de-tizku at ve-dorach
l'alma de-atei
or you and your entire generation will get עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
So that's sort of like a trick question. So there's only one
right answer to that. So אמר, amar, he said, דניזכו אנא ודריי
לעלמא דאתי. de-nizku ana ve-darai l'alma de-atei. No, I want me and
my generation, which also I think shows again, you know, the self-sacrifice
for the sake of others. So before he was giving over four
hundred teachings. Now he's giving over four hundred years in order for
the benefit of his entire generation. So אמר להו הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amar lehu HaKadosh Baruch Hu, so God said to them, whoever they
is, the heavenly angels, תנו לו זו וזו. tenu lo zu ve-zu.
Give him both. Okay? Since you made the right choice, you get
both the four hundred years and everybody else's merit. All right, but
anyway, a very powerful story about the dedication and of a rabbi,
a teacher to make sure that his students really know what they
are being taught. אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, said Rav Chisda,
אין תורה נקנית אלא בסימנים. ein Torah niknet ela be-simanim. So this
actually goes a little bit back to the earlier point about like
precise language and using mnemonics. So how do you remember thing? You
make mnemonics. You make סימנים, simanim, signs. שנאמר שימה בפיהם, shene'emar simah
be-fihem, place it in their mouths, אל תקרי שימה אלא סימנה, al
tikrei simah ela simanah, its signs. שמע רב תחליפא ממערבא, shama Rav
Tachlifa mi-ma'arava, so Rav Tachlifa from the west, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
heard this, אזל ואמרה קמיה דרבי אבהו, azal ve-amrah kammei de-Rabbi Abbahu,
he said it to Rabbi Abbahu. Oh, you know, in בבל Bavel
they say make סימנים simanim and they quote this פסוק. pasuk. אמר,
amar, he said, אתון מהתם
מתניתו, atun me-hatam masnitu, you learn it out from this. אנן מהכא
מתנינא לה, anan me-hacha masninan lah,
here's where we learn out this idea from. הציבי לך ציונים, hatzivi
lach tziyunim, make for yourself signs like signposts. שימי לך וכו' simi
lach ve-chulu etc. עשו ציונים לתורה, asu tziyunim la-Torah, make נציונים natziyunim
ציונים, tziyunim, right? ציון Tziyun is ציון, Tzion, is זין, zayin, ציונים.
tziyunim.
Make for yourself signposts for the Torah. So we get it from
a different פסוק, pasuk, not exactly clear what difference it makes which
פסוק pasuk you get it from. Anyway, ומאי משמע, u-mai mashma, and
where do you get this idea דהאי ציון לישנא דסימנא הוא de-hai
tziyun lishna de-simanah hu is in the sense of a sign? דכתיב
ראה עצם אדם ובנה אצלו ציון, de-chtiv ra'ah etzem adam u-vanah etzlo
tziyun, because it says they saw a bone of a man and
they built by it like a marker. So you see it's that
means a marker. Okay, רבי אלעזר אמר מהכא, Rabbi Elazar amar me-hacha,
here's where you know the idea of making signs. אמור לחכמה אחותי
את, emor la-chochmah achoti at, say to wisdom you are my sister,
ומודע לבינה תקרא u-muda la-vinah tikra and call for understanding like a
friend or familiar. עשו מודעים לתורה, asu moda'im la-Torah,
you should make like מודע muda signs, informers for the Torah. So
make for yourself again these things that it will help you like
remember where things are, remember things. You know, that's what they say
is like a primary memory aid, right? Is that you think about
pictures and you think about strange picture and you know and that
and you associate it with things and that helps you remember things.
Okay, רבא אמר עשו מועדים לתורה. Rava amar asu mo'adim la-Torah. Not
מודע muda but מועד, mo'ed,
reversing the letters. Make proper times for the Torah, which means רש"י
Rashi says,
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, קבעו עתים לתלמידיכם שיהיו יודעים עת
לבוא ולשנות. kiv'u itim l'talmideichem she-yihyu yode'im et lavo ve-lishnot. Have the
fixed time for when you're giving class like דף יומי. Daf Yomi.
Okay, everybody knows this is the time we come and we learn.
So it's sort of like קובע עתים לתורה koveia itim la-Torah but
here with a little switch on the person teaching others. And about
memory, so the importance about fixed times that sort of focuses you
maybe like before you're not distracted, you're totally focused. והיינו דאמר רב
דימי בר חמא דף נ"ה עמוד א'. ve-hainu de-amar Rav Dimi bar
Chama daf nun hey amud aleph. That's what רב דימי בר חמא
Rav Dimi bar Chama says. בר דוסא, bar Dosa, מאי דכתיב, mai
de-chtiv, what's meant by the פסוק pasuk לא בשמים היא ולא מעבר
לים היא? lo va-shamayim hi ve-lo me-ever la-yam hi? לא בשמים היא,
lo va-shamayim hi, it's not up in the heavens, that means שאם
בשמים היא, she-im ba-shamayim hi, were it up in the heavens, אתה
צריך לעלות אחריה. atah tzarich la-alot achareha.
You would have to go up after, meaning it happens not to
be in the heavens, so you don't have to go up after
it. But were it in the heavens, that would be your responsibility.
ואם מעבר לים היא, ve-im me-ever la-yam hi, and had it been
across the ocean, אתה צריך לעבור אחריה. atah tzarich la-avor achareha. You'd
have to go after it. So the point being that this is
about the self-sacrifice that you would be required to do in order
to acquire Torah. So similarly this idea of making signs and fixed
times and dedicating yourself to make sure that you do everything in
order that you will, רש"י Rashi says, להערים בתחבולות כדי שיתקיים התורה
בלומדיה. l'harim be-tachbulot kedei she-yitkayem ha-Torah be-lomdeha.
You have to like, you know, be sort of sly, crafty in
all types of devices in order to make sure that you learn
Torah and that your students remember the Torah that they are being
taught. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
Rava says, לא בשמים היא, lo va-shamayim hi, it's not in the
heavens, לא תמצא במי שמגביה דעתו עליה כשמים. lo timtza be-mi she-magbi'ah
da-ato aleha ka-shamayim. Going back to other themes we said before about
making yourself humble. The Torah will not be found in those that,
you know, that lift, you know, lift themselves up to the heavens,
that make themselves so haughty. ולא תמצא, ve-lo timtza, and it won't
be found, maybe you could say a true Torah won't be found
in those people, ולא תמצא במי שמרחיב דעתו עליה כים. ve-lo timtza
be-mi she-marchiv da-ato aleha ka-yam.
Somebody who broadens himself over it like the ocean, which sort of
means like also the earlier theme, you just try to cover more
and more and more ground and you don't do חזרה. chazarah. So
it's very these themes very much playing back on all the earlier
things. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim
hi, it's not in the heavens, לא תמצא בגסי רוח, lo timtsa
begassei ruach,
similar to the first point of רבא, Rava, you won't find it
amongst the haughty, ולא מעבר לים היא, v'lo me'ever layam hi, לא
תמצא לא בסחרנין ולא בתגרין, lo timtsa lo b'sachranin v'lo b'tagrin, you
won't find it among the, you know, among the, you know, the
merchants and you know the local merchants or the merchants that go
from city to city. Obviously, you know, if you have another profession
and particularly if it's a profession that requires a lot of travel,
you will not have the ability to have the time and the
focus to learn תורה Torah as you need. Okay, so that is
the end of that very fascinating digression about the מעברין מעברין, me'avrin
me'avrin, but in the end, you know, a lot of focus more
than like other passages, like we're familiar with extensive passages on the
importance of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. I think what's distinctive here is
the concern about how do you remember the תורה Torah that you're
learning and all of the issues about various practical suggestions, you know,
repeating it, saying it out loud, signs, etc. and also some sort
of like more moral points about haughtiness and so on. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara gets back finally to the משנה. Mishna. תנו
רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, rabbis taught: כיצד מעברין את הערים, Keitzad me'avrin et
ha'arim, how do you sort of, not מערבין me'arvin but מעברין, me'abrin,
how do you make a pregnant the city or add a limb
to based on the גרסא, girsa, but how do you sort of
expand right the parameters of the city for this? So, ארוכה כמות
שהיא. arucha k'mot'sha hi. If it's long then then you keep it
that way. So what does that mean exactly? We'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara. So this first starts the ברייתא. braita. עגולה, Agula, if
it's circular, עושים לה זויות מרובע, osim la zaviyot meruba, you make
it corners. So that's very simply the point that you square it
off, right? There's a little picture in רש"י Rashi that way. Okay,
so that's to you benefit the corners.
מרובעת, Meruba'at, if it's already square, אין עושים לו זויות, ein osim
lo zaviyot, you don't make it corners, which is like okay obviously
it's already square. We'll see what the גמרא Gemara will explain all
of this.
הייתה רחבה מצד אחד וקצרה מצד אחר, Hay'ta rechava mitzad echad v'ketzara
mitzad acher, it was wide at one end and narrow at the
other end. So you imagine like a trapezoid, right? וקצרה מצד אחר,
v'ketzara mitzad acher, רואין אותה כאילו היא שוה, ro'in otah k'ilu hi
shaveh, you look at it as as though it's a as though
it's equal. What's what's that called? A regular, what what is it
called?
No, aren't there names for that when it's sort of right angles
at all sides?
That's a rhombus—no that's a—If
you have a trapezoid, right, you make it שוה, shaveh, you make
it into a rectangle. I know that's called a rectangle but what
are שוה shavehs called that are all right angles? There's a word
for that. Isn't that normal or something, whatever it is. Anyway, fine.
Rectangular parallelepiped. Okay, whatever.
Anyway, moving on. So you square it off so that it is
so that it's equal, equal length and width on all sides. Okay,
היה
בית אחד יוצא כמין פגום, Hayah bayis echad yotzei k'min pagum, if
one house was jutting out like a like an indentation, it's funny
indenting into the into the outside I guess, או שני בתים יוצאין
כמין שני פגומין o shnei batim yotzin k'min shnei pagumim or two
houses jutting out, רואין אותן כאילו חוט מתוח עליהם, ro'in otam k'ilu
chut matuach aleihem, you look at it as though a string is
is stretched from them, ומודד ממנו ולהלן אלפיים אמה, u'moded mimeno u'lahalan
alpayim amah, and you and you measure from it onwards 2,000 אמה.
amah.
So which is basically very simply if you've got
the city
like a simple square city and you've got one house that juts
out, so you make a you as though there was a string
and basically you just extend the city limit as to the far
to the most far eastern house, the most far northern house and
so on. Okay.
Okay, הייתה עשויה כמין קשת, Hay'ta asuya k'min keshet, if it was
like a rainbow or bow, או כמין גם, o k'min gam, or
like a גם, gam, a gamma, which is, you know, a Greek
letter which is basically a, you know, is this is this the
way you write a gamma? Yep. Okay, a gamma or a rainbow.
Alright, if that's the way the city looked, רואין אותה כאילו היא
מלאה בתים וחצירות, ro'in otah k'ilu hi m'leya batim u'chatzeirot,
you look at the open space as if it's completely filled with
houses and courtyards, ומודד ממנו ולהלן אלפיים אמה, u'moded mimeno u'lahalan alpayim
amah, you get 2,000 אמה. amah. So basically if all the houses
are here,
you nevertheless look at it as if there were houses here all
in this middle and basically you're just saying you draw a line
from there and you go 2,000 אמה amah from there. And similarly
here, you look at it as if all of this is filled
and you draw these two lines and you and you go 2,000
אמה amah in each direction. Okay, so it's just an extreme case
of a jutting out house, right as it were. Here just you
know if you think of it like okay if this were the
city it's like you have a lot of jutting outs going on
here. It's the same basic principle but it's just an extreme case
of it. You basically square it all off based on the most
you know eastern, western, northern, and southern positions and you square it
off.
Yes, why wouldn't you square off the the semi-circular one?
Oh oh you do actually that's a good point, meaning this is
where you start go that's an excellent point, this is where you
start going
south, right, you
don't just say. That, right? And when
you measure east, right, you're measuring it also like from here and
west from here. So you actually do. But the חידוש chiddush is,
this we sort of already knew. The חידוש chiddush here was, is
that, you know, even though there's this big open space, you don't
treat it as though there's no real city there, you know, it's
just open space. Because there's so much more
open space than there is city.
Yes. Did the גמרא Gemara go and talk about the nature of
the open space, like does it have to be buildable?
Well, it will talk about how big the space is.
I don't think it'll talk about... Why would you build a city
like this?
Right, right, maybe there's a big mountain in the middle or something.
It's a good point. I mean the גמרא Gemara does not talk
about its ability to be built over. It does talk about the
distance from one to the other, so we'll see to some degree,
but that's an excellent point, like maybe there's, right, a mountain or
a body of water or something. All right, so let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Now,
okay.
אמר
מר: Amar Mar: So going back to the ברייתא baraita and now
we're going to analyze it. ארוכה כמות שהיא, Arucha kemot shehi, if
it's long, you leave it the way it is. פשיטא, Peshita, obvious.
לא צריכא דאריכא וקטינא. Lo tzericha dearicha uktina. No, the point is
it's long and narrow. It's like a very, you know, it's a
rectangle, it's a very thin rectangle. מהו דתימא, Mah deteima, I might
think למיתב לה פותיא כאורכה, lemitav lah putya keorchah, give it width
like its length, meaning don't just make everything into a rectangle, maybe
you should make everything into a square. Okay. No, that far we're
not going to go. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, so it's
telling you not. So the idea is you make a rectangle around
them, not a square around them. I mean if it happens to
be a square, fine. Okay. מרובעת אין עושין לה זויות, Merubaat ein
osin lah zaviyot, if it's already squared, you don't make corners. פשיטא,
Peshita, obviously. Why, I mean, you know, if it's already a rectangle,
what do you need to do? לא צריכא, Lo tzericha, it needs
to tell you for the following case: דמרובעא ולא מרבעא בריבוע עולם.
demurbaat velo merabaat beribua olam. It is a square or a rectangle,
but not based on the compass points. ריבוע עולם Ribua olam means
the compass points. The, you know, מהו דתימא, Mah deteima, I might
think לרבעה כריבוע עולם, lerabaah keribua olam, you should maybe adjust it
to the compass points. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that you
do not. So means, if this is, you know, if this is
due north, and if you have a city that goes like this,
you do not get to make, since it's already the right shape,
the rectangle, you do not get to do this. Right? Since it's
already the right shape. So therefore, since you don't have to square
it off because you what you have to square it off, you
square it off based on the compass points. But if you don't
need to square it off, you don't get the benefit of squaring
it off by the compass points and therefore, you know, you would
sort of... so how would you do it? I guess... well, that's
an interesting question, because still where would you... I guess you would
start based on... it depends where you would start from. It's an
interesting question. But I assume it would start from where you would
start from. You know, you would what you do is you would
draw 2,000 אמות amot out and you would go like this, right?
And that would be your 2,000 אמות amot out and that would
be your limit, okay? As opposed to had you squared it off,
right, then basically this would also have been squared off and then
you would have gotten all of that. Okay, so that's the difference.
So if it's already a rectangle, you don't get the benefit of
squaring it off according to the compass points. But if it's not
a rectangle, rather you have to square it off, and then you
square it off according to the compass points. So as I said,
at home I did the, I printed off these maps and I
squared them up, but I forgot to bring them. But basically, if
you think about New York City, right, I don't know, what does
New York City look like? It's sort of... Just like that. Manhattan,
yeah. It looks something like Israel, actually. So anyway, so anyway, you
know, and here you got, right, and here, you know, you've got
whatever, the Hudson, here you've got New Jersey and all of that,
and right, the Henry Hudson, and here you've got Riverdale, whatever, the
Bronx, right, and all of this, right? That's sort of what New
York City looks like. So if you go ahead and you square
it off, right, you've got, this is the northernmost or whatever, like
assuming, I'm assuming the gap here at the, what's this river called?
Spuyten Duyvil. Spuyten Duyvil, whatever, anyway. Basically, you can't count to the
next house if it's or the next city, if we consider that
another city, if it's more than about 100 to 200 feet.
I'm assuming that the gap at
that back bridge is longer than that. So that's the northernmost, okay.
This is the southernmost, right? This is probably going to be the
easternmost and this is the westernmost. And basically, if you go ahead
and do that, you've got a good part of New Jersey, a
good part of what is this, Queens or something? Brooklyn or something?
Yeah, whatever, anyway. So basically, you can really like walk from Manhattan
over the
bridge into New Jersey on
שבת Shabbat because it's all within that square.
But can you walk to Riverdale? What?
Can you walk to Riverdale? Yes, so from Riverdale...
George Washington Bridge is over 3,000 feet long, but that's less than
2,000 אמות amos though. Right? Yeah, that's less than 2,000 אמות, amos,
but
how far can you go from here?
You have to
look because if this
is built up like this, it squares off the Bronx. Right? Exactly.
And that helps us to walk from if this is built up
like this, you go to the extent of where it's built up,
you know, yeah. So you look in the maps it'll but no
it is but it'll work. It's not always true though that it's
not always true that it works out the same in both directions
because if you could imagine, let's just imagine for a moment that
the way this looked was was like this, right? Let's just imagine
that that's the way that looked, right? So that's New Jersey. So
if you start in Manhattan, you get that corner of New Jersey,
right? But if you start in New Jersey, again, our imaginary
New Jersey, right, it could be, right, that you don't get into
Manhattan. And that might be a problem with Manhattan.
We may be able to walk to Manhattan, but Manhattan may not
be able to walk here. Oh, that's a good point, because that
would go by the northernmost point. It's a good question. But people
do come from Manhattan to Riverdale. Yeah, but the way it actually
is if you're in Washington
Heights you're in Manhattan and the Bronx at the same time because
of the boundaries of each. Oh, you mean overlapping. So you're already
starting in the Bronx. Oh, that's a good point. Why do you
say you're starting in Manhattan? Which is right. If you're here, right,
if you're here, if you do that, right, so then people that
are living here, right, are already starting as long as you don't
go out the boundary like this.
Okay. I've got to figure that one out, but okay, you get
the idea. Some survey for another day. All right, so now let's
continue. All right, that's an excellent point that you're starting already in
overlapping תחומים. tchumin. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, מודה, Modeh, we just did it. היה בית אחד יוצא כמין
פגום, Haya bayis echad yotze k’min pagum, last narrow line, if one
house was going out jutting out, או שתי בתים יוצאין כמין פגום,
o shetei batim yotzin k’min pagum, or two houses. So then you
draw a line from the jutting out. השתא בית אחד אמרת שתי
בתים מיבעיא, Hashta bayis echad amarta shetei batim mibaia, if one house
certainly if it's two houses, because it doesn't assume that it means
two houses stacked up. It means if you have the case here,
right, of the one house jutting out, so it means and or
if you have two houses jutting out. So it says of course
that's even more of a reason to draw the line there, right,
if it's two houses jutting out. Again, it doesn't mean that they're
jutting out stacked. So it says, השתא בית אחד אמרת שתי בתים
מיבעיא לא צריכא משתי רוחות. Hashta bayis echad amarta shetei batim mibaia
lo tzricha mishtei ruchos. They're jutting out in opposite directions. מהו דתימא
רוח אחת אמינא משתי רוחות לא אמינא, Mahu dema ruach achas amina
mishtei ruchos lo amina, maybe say one direction, but two directions I
wouldn't say, again particularly because it's just one house, so maybe it's
like like you know sort of just disregarded. It's not like the
real city parameters. It's one little house that sticks out. So maybe
I wouldn't go so far as to say it in two opposite
directions. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that you do. Which means that if
one is jutting out in the east and one is jutting out
in the west, you get the benefit of both extensions. Okay, you're
able to do it, you know, twice. And the חידוש chiddush here
being that it's not even the real fundamental the עיקר ikar city,
it's one little house. All right. Now, היתה עשויה כקשת, Haisa asuya
k’keshes, if it is made like a bow, או כמין גא"ם, o
k’min gams, or like a gamma, רואין אותה כאילו היא מלאה בתים
וחצרות, ro'in osa k'ilu hi male'a batim v'chatzeros, you look at it
as if it's filled with houses and courtyards, ומודדין הימנו ולהלן אלפיים
אמה, u'modidin mimeno u'halan alpaim ama, and then you go from, you
know, from the outermost houses 2,000 אמה. ama. All right, so אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, so now Rav Huna says, here he's
going to put some limits on this. עיר העשויה כקשת, Ir ha'asuya
k'keshes, if it's made like a bow, אם יש בין שני ראשיה
פחות
מארבעת אלפים אמה, im yesh bein shenei
rosheha pachas
m'arba'as alapim ama, if
there is between the two sort of edges of the bow, the
two tips of the bow, right between here, here and here, I'll
just draw another picture. Okay. Here's our bow. He said if between
this edge and this edge, the
last sort of, you
know, part, if there's if there's less than
4,000 אמה, ama, okay, then
it's all
considered one thing, because in theory you could have put
an עירוב eiruv here
and it would be possible to get from this point to this
house and from this point to that house, okay, or less than
or equal to 4,000 אמה. ama. Okay, so so then it's okay,
then it's essentially considered like they're all together and it's all one
city. All right, פחות מארבעת אלפים אמה, pachas m'arba'as alapim ama, or
less than 4,000 אמה, ama, מודדין לה מן היתר, modidin la min
hayeter, then you count the measurement from the יתר yeter as like
the string, the extension, the outermost houses. And if not... Then you
have to go from the bow, which means that then you don't
consider that this is the end of the city and therefore you
basically make, you know, a similar תחום tchum which would basically, you
know, just look like this, you know, sort of, you know, that
would be your 2,000 אמה ama תחום. tchum. So every house would
go with its own 2,000, you know, essentially, אמות amos or however
that would work. Okay. So what? What's the someone's point being in
the city? Right, so in that case if you were in the
city, it would be the same for everybody. I'm sorry? If you
weren't in the city? Right. Well, the point here is that no,
exactly, you could go—you could go if you start here, you could
go here, you know, you get the whole parameters
of the city, but you don't get, you know, so...
Now the funny thing is,
though, why don't we then say that like, do we apply this
to
all funny configured, like all cities, it needs to be 4,000 אמה
ama from one extension to the other? It seems and we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara that it's particularly here because there's so much
open space that maybe we don't even consider it one city. And
that seems to be the concern about bringing all of this stuff
together as opposed to like a real big solid block, like Manhattan
even if it's at an angle would be different. Okay. So... yes.
If it's more than 4,000 אמה, ama, but as you go up
closer towards the peak of a bow, it'll get less than 4,000.
Excellent, excellent point. So תוספות Tosafos says that if this is 5,000,
it's actually a מחלוקת ראשונים. machlokes Rishonim. But if up by the
time you get
here you're at 4,000, תוספות Tosafos says you're
allowed to
start here for everyone
and go down like that. You're allowed to start when it gets
to 4,000, then you start measuring. That's what תוספות Tosafos says, others
disagree.
And the people at each extreme of the bow, can they walk—they
can walk through the city, they can walk this way and then
down? Yes, exactly. Exactly. Right here, you could get to the other
house by going like this. You just can't get to it by
going like that. The גמרא Gemara is actually going to discuss that.
Actually, in that scenario you could, because the 5,000 people are within,
you know, you're within the תחום tchum of the city. If this
is all included in the תחום tchum
of the city, then these people can walk through the open area.
Here, right, here you can walk through the open area? Yeah, because
it's within here.
No, but you can't be in this void! Why not? If you're
part of the city and the תחום tchum of the city... Oh,
once you do the 4,000, right. According to תוספות, Tosafos, once you
do the 4,000, you also get that and that allows you then.
That is correct. According to תוספות, Tosafos, once
you do that, you will be able to.
But since you couldn't without that,
you
cannot
start the תחום tchum from down here because
that's—they're not considered unified at that point.
They're only considered unified up at this point. Okay. Yes, so now
the גמרא Gemara says, where are we? Okay. ואם לאו מודדין לה
מן הקשת. Ve'im lav modedin la min hakeshes. ומי אמר רב הונא
הכי? Umi amar Rav Huna hachi? Did Rav Huna really say that
that 4,000 אמה ama is enough to consider it unified and bring
it all together? It has to be less than, not less than
and equal. There has to be an overlap of the two תחומין
tchumin is the way רש״י Rashi explains it. So does he really
say that less than 4,000 is sufficient to bring it together? והאמר
רב הונא, Veha'amar Rav Huna, but Rav Huna says: חומת עיר שנפרצה
במאה ארבעים ואחת ושליש. Chomas ir shenifretza beme'ah arba'im ve'achas veshlish. If
you have a city that the wall broke in the city on
opposite ends and there's a big like empty spot in the city.
You have a little picture like that in רש״י. Rashi. Okay, basically
you had something that used to be a whole—a walled city filled
with houses, okay, and then came along, I don't know what happened,
and there became a gap, okay, there in the city. The walls
were broken and there were no houses in the middle. Is it
going to be considered a unified city for תחומין? tchumin? And he
says if the space between it is how much? 140, what is
it? ואחת ושליש, ve'achas veshlish, right? 141 and a third. Right, that
that is okay. Now, why is that? We are going to find
out. How do you define when a house is considered part of
the city or not? What are the edges of the city limit?
Right, so we talked about what types of houses, about cemeteries and
this and that, if there's some—if it's a place that's habitable, that's
used for living and so on. But how close does it have
to be to the other house to be considered part of the
city? So the answer is 70 and 2/3 אמה. ama. So if
you've got a city like this, right, and you have some like
outlying houses, if they're within 70 and 2/3, then it's considered an
extension, a part of the city. And if it's more than that,
it's outside of the city. Where do we get 70 and 2/3?
You might remember, you might remember our favorite—one of our favorite measurements
in ערובין Eruvin is בית סאתים, beis sasayim, a space to sort
of plant two סאה, se'ah, and that is learned from the—right, and
that if you have a space like that that's not made for
habitation, it creates problems, you know, you know
about making an עירוב eiruv in
that space and so on. Okay, now that is learned from the
חצר chatzer of the... If you were to turn that into a
square, what's a square root of 5,000? It's roughly 70 and two-thirds.
Okay, so for whatever reason, that becomes the measure of the distance
of houses. So what he's saying is, if here, even if there's
no houses between them, if here there is an overlap of, if
you took that space that you normally have, the 70 and two-thirds
from this side and the 70 and two-thirds from this side, and
there was some overlap, then it's considered as if they're all brought
together because it's not just a house, it's unifying a city, so
you give each half-city as it were 70 and two-thirds, and if
they overlap, it's one city. Okay, so anyway, there you see in
order to unify a city, you need 70 and two-thirds. Why here
does he say you can get up to 4,000 אמות? amos? There's
a pretty big difference between 70 and two-thirds, 141 and a third,
and 4,000, right? So what's the difference? So the answer should be
obvious, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. במאה וארבעים
ואחת ושליש, B'meah v'arbaim v'achas v'shlish, that then it can be unified.
Okay, so where were we? So he says, אמר רבה בר עולא,
Amar Rabbah Bar Ulla, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. Why
is it 141 or is it 4,000? כאן ברוח אחת כאן משתי
רוחות. Kan b'ruach achas kan mishtei ruchos. The question is one side
or two sides. Meaning, here the problem is that the gap basically
is sort of like, this is totally fine on three sides of
it. There's like a problem on one side, so it's closing off
that one side gap. Here it's considered to be, you could still
say I don't know, it's one side that's, but anyway, it's considered
to be that the problem is not just it was all okay
and there was one gap. Wait, that wouldn't work, then it would
be the opposite. Why do we allow you to get more here?
Hold on one second, let me double check רש״י. Rashi. No, it's
the opposite point, hold on. No, I'm sorry, it's the opposite point,
right? Here basically the point is like this. Here you do have
a unified, right, here the whole city is connected. It's just that
at one side of it there's like a break between it, but
fundamentally everything is connected. Here, the stuff on this side is not
at all, there's no way that there's any connectivity between this and
this. So here it's basically divided in both sides. This is separate
from that and that's separate from this. Here as it were in
one side, rather the side, whatever here, one aspect of it everything
is connected, it's just another one aspect they're separate, but in another
aspect they're all connected. So therefore here it's easier to unify and
you have up to 4,000 אמות. amos. Yes, so that example on
the left should mean that New York City should be at least
four different cities because of the rivers. Right, because of that, that's
why I said before, is it more than 200 feet? Those rivers
that break it from 200 feet, right, means that you cannot sort
of combine all the different boroughs into one big city. Right, so
that's what you asked, is there a gap of built up space
of 140 whatever is about 200 feet. Okay, but then but even
though you do that, as we saw, once you do the box,
you wind up getting into the other boroughs anyway. But yeah. But
this should be a problem for those teenagers who walk from Brooklyn
here on שמיני עצרת. Shmini Atzeres. Well, you have to see, go
look at a map, do the box, and it might work out
because you look, maybe when you're looking at this part of New
York City, maybe it's all I don't know, maybe you have continuous
build up all the way there. Yeah, Long Island doesn't go that
far. All right, you'll take a look at the map and you'll
figure it out. Okay, fine. All right, anyway, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. All right. מאי קא משמע לן? Mai ka
mashma lan? And now back to just that other statement of רב
הונא. Rav Huna. The basic point of רב הונא Rav Huna is
what is he teaching us? נותנין קרפף, Nosin karpaf, קרפף karpaf is
like a little buffer or whatever. There's got to be a better
word for קרפף. karpaf. How do they translate קרפף karpaf there? They
didn't translate. קרפף, Karpaf, wonderful. נותנין קרפף לזו וקרפף לזו, Nosin karpaf
lazu v'karpaf lazu, that to each city you give this slightly little
land outside. Okay, the 70 and two-thirds of each, which is קרפף
karpaf is the general word saying that's the gap that you can
have in order that another house is considered part of your city.
So אמר רב הונא חדא זימנא, Amar Rav Huna chada zimna, רב
הונא Rav Huna already said it, דתנן, d'tnan, we taught in a
משנה, Mishnah, top of מ״ב. Mem-Beis. נותנין קרפף לעיר דברי רבי מאיר.
Nosin karpaf la'ir divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
even if there's no house outside the city, right, remember how when
we were learning between because you get your four אמות amos and
then you get your 2,000 after your four, and then there was
a question even maybe you get two אמות amos after that, the
קרפף, karpaf, so anyway so what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says is
when you measure a city... Here's your city, you don't start here
for the two thousand, but since were there a house after the
seventy and two thirds point, the קרפף karfof had there been a
house anywhere up to here, it would have been considered part of
the city, so therefore, that's the sort of space around the city,
the fields of the city as it were, that is part of
the city. And therefore you start after your seventy and two thirds
is when you start. Okay, so like he's extending. Right, that's the
point. Oh, two thousand, boom, this and after this and after this,
right. And then four. So even if there's no house, you give
them the seventy, you give every city the seventy and two thirds.
Okay. A good point, like margins on your paper. וחכמים אומרים vachachamim
omrim and the חכמים chachamim say, לא אמרו קרפף אלא בין שתי
העיירות. lo amru karfof ela bein shtei ha'ayarot. No, it's only good
to combine two cities, or for a house in the city, but
you don't always give, but if the city is already the parameters
are defined, you don't add another seventy and two thirds. And okay,
now what does it mean to combine two cities? ואתמר ve'itmar and
it was taught: רב הונא אמר קרפף לזו וקרפף לזו. Rav Huna
amar karfof lezu vekarfof lezu. If you have to combine two cities,
then you give seventy and two thirds to each city and if
it overlaps, they're considered combined, which means if the gap is 141
or less. Okay, so that if you if with giving the קרפף
karfof you combine it, they overlap, then you're allowed to combine. So
you normally don't give a קרפף karfof if there's not a house
there, but you do to determine if a city is combined with
another city. That's what he says. וחייא בר רב אמר אין נותנים
אלא קרפף אחד לשניהם. veChiyya bar Rav amar ein notnim ela karfof
echad lishneihem. No, that only if there's seventy and two thirds or
less between them do you combine them. You don't give each one
of them a קרפף. karfof. But what do you see? You see
that רב הונא Rav Huna says that you give the same point
141 between two cities to combine it. So why did he have
to tell me in both cases? A normal case of two cities
and a case of a city that broke through in the middle.
It's the same הלכה halacha that you give 141 to consider combined.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say צריכא, tzricha, he needed to
tell me both cases. אי אשמעינן הכא, ei ashme'inan hacha, had he
said the case of the one city that got, you know, broken
in the middle, משום דהוי לה צד היתר מעיקרא, mishum dehava lah
tzad heter mei'ikara, because it used to be okay, it used to
be one city. So it's easier even after there's a break, maybe
you'd be more lenient and still considering it to be one city.
אבל התם, aval hatam, but when things really start off as separate
cities, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe he wouldn't say 141, maybe he'd
need them to be closer, because fundamentally those are separate cities. אי
אשמעינן התם, ei ashme'inan hatam, had he said there you go by
141, משום דדחיקא תשמישתייהו, mishum dedachika tashmishtaihu, since it's two cities, every
city gets a margin, you know, every city needs to breathe a
little bit, so gets a margin. So that's why each city has
its own קרפף karfof and therefore if they overlap you're okay. But
אבל הכא דלא דחיקא תשמישתייהו, aval hacha dela dachika tashmishtaihu, here if
it used to be one city, so you already needed some breathing
space here, this part in the middle used to be built up,
so maybe you need some breathing space here, but never here. So
maybe it doesn't make sense to say you're each entitled to seventy
and two thirds when it breaks. So צריכא, tzricha, you need both
cases. But at the end of the day, the point is that
this, to determine how much are is everything together, outlying houses have
to be within seventy and two thirds, which is about 100 feet,
and and separate cities according to at least this position can be,
you know, can be 200 feet apart and 141 אמות amos and
they're considered then to be one. וכמה הוי בין יתר לקשת? vechama
havi bein yeter lakeshet? Now, we said that the two tips of
the bow have to be within four thousand אמות. amos. How about
the the gap between the arc of the bow and right, so
we said that this has to be four thousand in order for
it to be considered combined. How about this? Is there a limit
of that distance? You know, because even if this is close, so
these are sort of maybe seen as continuous, maybe if this is
like I don't know ten, if this is like ten thousand אמות,
amos, maybe it's also there's so much you know whitespace that maybe
it's not considered to be one with the stuff way down below
it. So is there a limit? Is there an issue or not?
So it says, where were we? רבה בר רב הונא אמר אלפיים
אמה. Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar alpayim amah. It's two thousand אמות.
amos. It's interesting, not four thousand, because here you have each house
gives you two thousand, right? You have a house at each end
and it gives you two thousand and that gets you four. Here
you only have one house, there's nothing to link it to on
the bottom. There's no, it's all open space. So he says this
has to be two thousand for the, it's the same logic but
because there's only one house for it to all be considered unified.
רבא בריה דרבה בר רב הונא אמר Rava breih deRabbah bar Rav
Huna amar and רבא Rava the son of of רבה בר רב
הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna says, so wait, that's his, so that's,
so רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna said two thousand,
and רבה's Rabbah son רבא Rava said אפילו יתר מאלפיים. afilu yeter
me'alpayim. there's no limit. Once the ones at the bottom are considered
combined, then it combines the whole city and there's no limit how
high the top of the bow can be. אמר אביי כוותיה דרבא
בריה דרבה בר אבונא מסתברא Amar Abaye k'vassay d'Rava brei d'Rabba bar
Avuna mistavra that last position makes sense. דאי בעי הדר אתי דרך
פאצין d'ee bei hadar asit derech patzin because he says look, this
place is you know you can this is the point you could
always travel this way. You could always get to any point in
the in you know within the actual city itself. No point is
really completely separate. You're always able to travel via the city parameters
right and stay within. So once you've connected here at the bottom,
that's enough. You don't also need to connect to the top. He's
basically saying fundamentally it all still is connected you know along the
places where it's built up. Okay, so suppose you have a city
that's built according to the compass and it's bisected by let's say
a superhighway which is more than two hundred feet wide. Then you
have two cities. Right but if it's bisected but if it's not
yes, meaning you might it's a good point, meaning if it's exactly
like this right and then it's bisected by a highway, then theoretically
then you have two cities. But no city is made on the
compass points so you're going to get some you know so if
it more looks like this right you know and gets bisected or
something like that you're still going to be so you'll have two
cities but this city will look like this, that city will look
like that, and you will you're right that also won't count. Yeah
but there are ways in which it depends on the orientation of
the highway. Yeah depends on the orientation of the highway right. Right,
so if you've got exactly, so if you've got what would it
look like if you have it like this and the highway went
like this right so then you'd have this city and that city
but then you would square it off it'd be overlapping some space
of overlap. Without crossing bridges you'd have some overlap. Yeah, but it's
true it's true. Crossing bridges would play a factor if there's bridges
coming across the city. Right, so the Gemara does talk about bridges
and we're going to get to it but that's only if there's
a space to like to live on the bridge. The bridge by
itself doesn't extend the city parameters. It's always about habitats. You need
things that are you know habitats that extend it. Okay, so that's
actually the next discussion it's going to be quite interesting what's defined
as a habitat. Let's take a look. Okay, so now it goes
on. היו שם גדודיות גבוהות עשרה טפחים hayu sham gedudiyot gevohot asarah
tefachim if there were גדודיות gedudiyot ten טפחים tefachim high that counts.
So what are גדודיות? gedudiyot? That's what the Gemara says. מאי גדודיות?
mai gedudiyot? אמר רב יהודה שלש מחיצות שאין עליהן תקרה. Amar Rav
Yehuda shalosh mechitzot she'ein aleihen tikrah. Even if you have three walls
so like destroyed houses, even if you just have three walls without
a roof, even without a roof, but if it has three walls
so the basic point is places as Rashi says you don't have
to actually have people living there but just places that can be
inhabited and that are made for habitation. So this is made for
habitation. It's now been destroyed but as long as it still has
the potential of being inhabited and was made for habitation that counts.
איבעיא להו iba'ya lehu so the Gemara said שתי מחיצות ויש עליהן
תקרה מהו? shtei mechitzot v'yesh aleihen tikrah mahu? So three without a
roof, how about two with a roof? Would that still count? So
תא שמע ta shema come and hear. אלו שמתעברים עמה elu she'mitabrim
imah the following things are included in the city limits: נפש שיש
בה ארבע אמות על ארבע אמות nefesh she'yesh bah arba amot al
arba amot a נפש nefesh which is like a place by a
grave which they would have like little huts or whatever for people
who are watching the graves to live in. So again Rashi says
even if it's not currently inhabited it's made for that. So if
it's considered fit for habitation which is four אמות amot by four
אמות, amot, והגשר והקבר שיש בהם בית דירה v'hagesher v'hakever she'yesh bahem
beit dirah or bridge or cemetery that have places to you know
live there that you know whatever the I don't know like I
don't think the toll booth things count yeah because it's an interesting
question oh is it not four by four? Probably six feet by
six feet I don't know I think it's got a really you
might be right. It's an interesting question you know because what does
דירה dirah mean like if people stay in them and spend in
them do they have to sleep in them in order to be
considered a בית דירה? beit dirah? It's a good question whether the
toll booths would count. Anyway toll booths still wouldn't get you the
distance across the across the river. Okay, where were we? והגשר והקבר
שיש בהם בית דירה v'hagesher v'hakever she'yesh bahem beit dirah ובית הכנסת
v'beit haknesset and a synagogue by itself doesn't count it has to
have שיש בה בית דירה לחזן she'yesh bah beit dirah l'chazzan that
has a place for the you know for the sexton to be
living like you know the superintendent or whatever you know that he
he has a room in the basement. ובית עבודת כוכבים u'veit avodat
kochavim now listen to this even a even a pagan temple שיש
בה בית דירה לכומרין she'yesh bah beit dirah l'chomrin if it has
a place where the priests where you know live. So it doesn't
have to be Jewish now it doesn't have to be Jewish it
could even be עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Nevertheless it's part of the
city. So therefore if it's a place where people live even the
you know the the pagan priests it's totally fine but it has
to have a place where they live. והאורוות והאוצרות שבשדות v'ha'urvot v'ha'otzarot
shebasadot which are stables and storehouses out in the fields ויש בהם
בית דירה v'yesh bahem beit dirah if there's a place again a
place for somebody to live. והבורגנין שבתוכה v'haburganin shebetochah and the little
huts out in the field, והבית שבים v'habayit shebayam or if you
have a little house out on the ocean, רש״י Rashi says like
on a tiny little island, הרי אלו מתעברים עמה harei elu mitabrim
imah if they're within the seventy and two-thirds, which is implicit, they're
counted. All of those are because you have a sense of a
habitation. ואלו שאינן מתעברים עמה v'elu she'einan mitabrim imah the following not,
and this is basically just an exact negative of the previous list.
Okay, נפש שנפרצה משתי רוחותיה אילך ואילך nefesh sheniftzah mishtei ruchoteha elaf
ve'elaf if you have the remnant of a house that has two
walls, opposite walls destroyed, והגשר והקבר שאין להם בית דירה v'hagesher v'hakevesh
she'ein lahem beit dirah and a bridge or a cemetery whatever that
doesn't have a place for living. By the way, once you have
a house in the cemetery, this might be why the toll booth
story is relevant, because once you have a house in the cemetery,
you might be able to count the entire cemetery. Because and then,
so if you have a toll booth by the bridge, would that
give you actually the bridge? If it says a גשר gesher the
bridge counts and the cemetery counts if there's a place where somebody
lives. So it sounds and the גמרא Gemara is actually going to
say that later as well. So that's a very interesting question about
the toll booths. I'll have to look into that. Okay. ובית הכנסת
שאין לה בית דירה u'veit haknesset she'ein lah beit dirah or a
synagogue that does not have a place to live for the חזן,
chazan, ובית עבודת כוכבים שאין להם בית דירה לכומרים u'veit avodat kochavim
she'ein lahem beit dirah lakomarim or a house of idolatry that doesn't
have a place for the priests, והאורבות והאוצרות שבשדות שאין להם בית
דירה v'ha'orvot v'ha'otzarot shebasadot she'ein lahem beit dirah and stables and storehouses
that don't have any place to live, ובור ושיח ומערה וגדר ושובך
u'vor v'shiche v'mearah v'geder v'shovach or a well, you know, dug wells,
wells with a structure, ditches, walls, pigeon coops, שבתוכה shebetochah that are
out there in the field. All of those are, don't have any
place to live, even though they're significant structures. So you have, just
because you have some random wall, you know, you have a wall
outside of the city, it's actually an interesting point, you might think,
well, you know, I guess if it's a wall that surrounds the
city it's different. But if you just have like a whole, you
know, a wall out there and it's more than a, you know,
and it doesn't count to extend the city to the wall. It
has to be a place where people live. Okay, similarly, you know,
because you could understand people would think, you know, you have like
cemeteries around the outsides of
the city, walls outside of the city,
and logically you
consider it in your mind part
of the city. But if nobody is
living there, it doesn't count. Okay, where were
we? והבית שבספינה v'habayit shebisphinah and if you have a house on
a boat, you have like a yacht, okay, אין אלו מתעברים עמה
ein elu mitabrim imah that doesn't count. The reason for the yacht
is not because nobody lives in it, but because it doesn't have
a fixed location. So it cannot be considered part of the city.
Just wait. קתני מיהת ktani meihat but from that whole ברייתא Braita
what we did teach was, נפש שנפרצה משתי רוחותיה אילך ואילך. nefesh
sheniftzah mishtei ruchoteha elaf ve'elaf. If you have something that has two
walls broken through, you know, a destroyed house. מאי לאו דאיכא תקרה
mai lav de'ika tikra presumably it means even with a roof. So
that answers your question. That even with a roof, two walls is
not enough, you always need three walls. גמרא Gemara says, לא, lo,
not necessarily, דליכא תקרה. d'leika tikra. I'll say it means without a
roof. I'll say without a roof you need three
walls, with a roof two walls is good enough. בית שבים למאי
חזי? bayit shebayam lemai chazi? Now, if you have a little house
out on a tiny little island within 100 feet of
the city, what do you use that house for? Like nobody lives
there. So אמר רב פפא בית שעשוי לפנות בו כלים שבספינה.
amar Rav
Pappa
bayit she'asui lifnot bo kelim shebisphinah. No, what you use it for
is like if you're in a boat or whatever, you might go
ahead and use it to like offload some stuff from the boat
into the house. Which is a little funny though, because you would
still need to assume that somebody is living in that house, you
know, and he's there on that like, you know, maybe like on
that...
those little... what are the... the... lighthouse... no what are they called?
Lighthouses. You know. So maybe somebody lives so those are doing some
function that are helping the boats, but presumably it has to be
at least that it's made for somebody to live in because that
is consistently the theme here. Okay. Now where were we? אמר רב
פפא, amar Rav Pappa, we just did that. ומערה אין מתעברת עמה,
u'mearah ein mitaberet imah, so is it really true, one of the
things that was mentioned here which I think I ran over was
a cave. Is it really true a cave isn't part of the
city? והתני רבי חייא מערה מתעברת עמה, vehatani Rabbi Chiya mearah mitaberet
imah, it is included in the city. אמר אביי כי שיש בנין
על פיה. amar Abaye ki she'yesh binyan al piha. No, what we're
talking about is a cave that has a structure built near it
that's a house that's made for living. ותיפוק ליה משום בנין גופיה?
ve'teipokei mishum binyan gufah? So fine, so who needs the cave? Just
talk about the structure. לא, צריכא להשלים. lo, tzricha lehashel. You need
in order to supplement. So what does supplement mean? And this is
very important about the point I made before. רש״י Rashi says it
means that if even if the structure only is let's say two
אמות amot but then you go from the structure into the cave,
so the four אמות amot is with the combination of the cave,
but because it's built it's part of the cave that makes the
whole cave considered to be a בית דירה. beit dirah. תוספות Tosafot
however says, more significantly, that once you have the house built on
the cave, even if the only thing that's made for living is
the house, the whole cave now gets to be considered part of
the city. And that is what it sounded like before about the
cemetery and the bridges, once you have a place of habitation in
this space, this area, the whole area is part of the city,
so that actually is a fascinating question in terms of the toll
booths. The bridges and the toll booths, so I'll have to look
into that, yes. What if it extends for miles? What? How about
a mine? A mine. Yeah, big tunnel through the, horizontally sometimes for
miles. That's a good point. And do they have a בית דירה
beis dirah near them or? Especially at the entrance. Right. Do they,
do they, I mean they have a structure, right, right. But רשי
Rashi makes the point that it has to be a structure that's
made for habitation. Okay, let me just try to see one more
line here because and then, you know what, alright, I think we
will end here. So we're a little behind, but we'll pick up
here tomorrow.
Yes, go
ahead.